The energy shock hitting places like
Europe already where DHL CEO just said
the entire world is heading for a quote
tipping point. The race against time
that we've been talking about. But
focusing on Europe, economic sentiment
just crashed both commercial as well as
consumer. We've seen a jump in
unemployment in places like Scandinavia
and job losses returning to the UK along
with one of the most regrettable labor
market developments that we're all too
entirely familiar with over here in the
United States. The energy shock is
already starting to show up.
Now, Tobias Meyer, who's the head of
DHL, he told Bloomberg TV that consumers
in particular, they fail to fully grasp
the gravity of events like this until
something big and catchy happens to
focus their attention on the
implications. We ignore the elephant in
the room until the gigantic beast starts
kicking everything over. It's human
nature. He might as well be talking
about the stock market, too, not just
the consumers, not just the public.
Either way, it isn't until something
finally breaks that everyone starts to
take it seriously, and by then, it's
entirely too late. It's another way of
saying we're up against the clock. And
while we are, before we get to that
tipping point, everything looks
perfectly fine and resilient until it
doesn't. Even the negatives that we do
see piling up at this very early stage,
they're never fully appreciated until
that other shoe finally drops. Now,
Asia, we've talked about that one. Jet
fuel shortages that are going on right
now. Crazy oil prices. Europe, the focus
of our examination today, they're
already seeing the direct economic
fallout with consumer confidence in
quote free fall. That's the term the
European Commission used. It's not my
term. To go with even more escalating
unemployment. Flat beverage, not
inflation.
Sure, gasoline costs go up in the short
run, but because nobody can afford them,
they strangle activity, especially
employment. And keep in mind, the world
wasn't exactly in great shape when it
came to labor market to begin with flat
beverage showing up all over the place.
And also keep in mind, globally
synchronized. While this starts out or
it seems to start out in Asia and now
ripples into Europe, it's not going to
remain there because the only question
here is where that tipping point might
actually be and the state of the world
that we are in before we got to it is
every bit as important in determining it
as anything else.
The guys right, the clock is ticking on
the global energy shock and its possible
contribution or negative contribution to
employment. So much of the world was
already on the flat part of the beverage
curve, but because there hasn't been
that one singular event, a month or two
of just massive in your face layoffs,
the slow rise in joblessness has been
all but ignored in mainstream commentary
and certainly on the stock market. It
has been widespread already, much more
than you think.
Great degree of idling of workers and
labor far more than people have
appreciated. With employers worldwide
already in bad shape enough that they've
been cutting back on employees to begin
with, a prolonged period of heightened
gasoline, diesel, jet fuel, propane,
everything, it just adds another straw
to the back of an already shaky camel.
And not just oil prices and the price
effect, we also have to keep in mind
what literal demand destruction can do,
the physical supply shortage and how
they can directly force economy
participants to cut back and scale down
even where maybe they could otherwise
afford higher cost. That's really what
Mr. Meyer of DHL was talking about.
Again, the clock is ticking.
>> But if the underlying economic issue,
the lack of supply of energy, the 10-12
million barrels of crude oil per day, if
that is not resolved, it will come to
that tipping point and I think there
many people that are aware of that and
that's why also those discussions
are needed.
>> And And also right about the other part
of this too. The Trump administration,
among others, they understand very well
the economic downside and what that will
do to their election prospects coming up
this November. So, officials everywhere,
not just in the US, they really are
going to be doing whatever they can to
try to minimize the damage. But that's
not really the question. Authorities
won't be able to do much or anything if
the entire system does go by that
tipping point. I almost never do ads and
I say no to the vast majority of those
that are brought to my attention, but I
was thrilled to be able to work with
today's video sponsor, Monetary Metals.
And the reason is because they're
solving a big problem, one that I've
been highlighting for a very long period
of time. Gold is a safe haven, but other
than sitting in a vault, it doesn't do
anything. Monetary Metals fixes that.
They let you earn real yield paid in
physical gold without giving up
ownership. It's not a fund, it's not a
paper claim, it's your gold working for
you. Every month, more gold gets
deposited into your account. It's
simple, it's transparent, and it is
fully insured. If you believe in gold as
a long-term store of value as I do, this
changes everything. Go to
monetary-metals.com/snyder.
That's monetary-metals.com/snyder
for all the details. We absolutely thank
them for being the sponsor of today's
video, and now let's get back to it.
The focus therefore should be on where
that point really is. And as I've been
arguing, it's a lot closer than most
people think given the economy has been
in much, much worse shape than has been
appreciated, particularly from the lofty
view of the equity markets. And I keep
bringing that up because that's where
the vast majority of the public gets
their view of the economy. If stocks are
up, things must be just fine. Otherwise,
why else would stocks be going up? In
reality, the two have nothing to do with
each other. Stocks go up because people
buy stocks. That's it. I know it's a
tautology, but that's it. And once they
do go up and prices do rise, everyone
afterwards searches for a narrative to
explain why they did what they did. It
leads to the circular reasoning where
people pour into shares thinking the
economy will be great. Share prices
rise, which convinces investors to buy
more shares because higher prices must
mean the economy will be great. So,
stocks are booming because the economy
is, and we all know the economy is
because stocks are. Circular reasoning.
Now, Keynes, he was wrong about a great
many things, but he absolutely nailed
the stock market. And it's 10 times
worse nowadays. Just Google our good
friend Mike Green, if you don't already
know who he is, and if you don't already
know his work. But if you don't, make
sure you get yourself familiar with it
pronto, because equities tell us nothing
about the state of the economy. And
that's one reason why DHL's Meyer is
warning that maybe people should be a
little more attentive to the energy
shock and its tipping point, having
previously uncritically accepted what
really amounts to a false set of signals
and impressions. And that brings us to
the ZEW, which stands for ZEW, or a
bunch of German words that are very
difficult for English speakers to
pronounce, though we really want to
because they are impressive sounding
words like Wirtschaftsforschung.
Whatever that means, it means a center
for economic research. Either way, the
ZEW numbers were another set of
indications pointing toward maybe the
tipping point. So, the ZEW, widely
followed set of indicators on Germany
and Europe as a whole, commercial and
financial sentiment as well as
assessments of the current situation.
Now, the latter, the current situation,
is easy enough. Despite all the
glowingly positive statements from
European central bankers and politicians
telling us how Europe is finally picking
up and recovering after years of
forgetting how to grow that they never
admitted, the ZEW survey respondents are
not seeing any of it happen right now.
The current index, as you can see,
decisively ugly for years on end. And
while it has been slightly less so more
recently, it's hardly the categorical
switch to recovery that's been
repeatedly promised. Remember, the ECB's
Lagarde keeps saying Europe is in a good
place. So, while they don't see any
pickup in the economy today, they really
do want to believe Lagarde. Look at
German sentiment. They're a sucker for
any kind of policy \quote} stimulus. And
we've seen it time and again throughout
the years. Whether the stimulus comes
from the ECB, or in a few cases the
German government might announce some
economic aid. And so, ZEW in response,
the sentiment soared straight away, only
to be disappointed later on when it
doesn't do what it was supposed to do.
Now, that has been the case for the past
couple of years, and you can see it in
the huge divergence between the current
index, which is still solidly negative,
and the future sentiment index, which is
very positive for the future, at least
more positive than it's been in several
years,
but never much changing from right now.
And since last year's election, the
responsibility or reason for the
increase in sentiment, future sentiment,
last year's election, the new government
comes in from Friedrich Merz, and he
promises a Berlin bazooka in spending,
which has propelled that sentiment even
higher. But then comes along the energy
shock, and the positivity just vanishes.
The index for sentiment for Germany
crashing from plus 58.3 in February to
minus 0.5 last month in March to this
week's April reading of minus 17.2.
That's an enormous 75-point swing in
just two months. In fact, it's the
largest two-month slide since March and
April of 2022,
which was the last energy shock which
triggered the forgot-how-to-grow
recession, which was an outright
recession in Germany at the very least,
and Europe as well.
So, sentiment is even worse for Europe
as a whole. That index sank from plus 39
back in February to minus 20.4 as of the
latest data we just got for April. And
ZEW's president said, \quote} "The
economic consequences of the Iran war
for the German economy go far beyond
price increases. Businesses are
concerned about long-term shortages of
energy supply, and this discourages
investment and weakens the effect of
government stimuli." See what I mean
about infatuation with government
spending and central bank policies? It's
It's practically pathological.
But as much as the Germans really, and I
mean really want to buy into it, they
simply can't be happy about fake
stimulus and a fake stimulus future
which never's going to arrive given the
very real threat that's posed by more
than strictly oil prices. It's not just
the cost of gasoline, there's more to it
this time around.
So, it's not just commercial and
financial participants who are concerned
about the future now, it's also European
consumers because European consumer
sentiment, according to European
Commission, is in, quote, free fall. So,
using the latest figures that are out
today from the European Commission,
their consumer confidence index dropped
to minus 20.6. That's for April 2026,
down from minus 12.3 in February before
the start of the conflict. And just like
the ZEW's current assessment index, you
can see how consumer sentiment became
slightly less negative in the second
half of last year, but hardly anything
consistent with recovery or, you know,
Lagarde's good place. Quite the
contrary. But now minus 20.6 is the
worst reading since December 2022. So,
once again, mimicking the last energy
shock, therefore, on a path toward the
forgot how to grow recession repeat that
Europe experienced in 2022.
And the European Commission's press
release simply said, "Consumer
confidence continued its quote free
fall." And as much as we might want to,
it's hard to disagree with that
assessment. Confidence has crashed
because incomes are not growing. They
haven't been growing for a long time.
They haven't been enough to make up for
past price changes, let alone current
ones. Jobs are now disappearing, so
higher gasoline costs are going to make
it harder for consumers to spend on
other items, other goods and services,
along with, as consumers know,
tightening the screws on their
employers. Employers that have already
been struggling for years alongside
consumers. You throw some gasoline costs
on there and it just makes the situation
even worse. And that's something that
even official governments and official
estimates have been trying to pick up on
and trying to get ahead of over in
Europe as well. The German government
slashing its estimates for GDP growth in
2026 already, just 7 weeks into the
energy shock.
Quote, "Output is set to grow by half a
percent this year," the economy ministry
in Berlin said on Wednesday. "That
compares with a January projection for a
1% expansion." The ministry also revised
its outlook for next year down to 9/10
of percent from 1.3%. The escalation in
the Middle East and the war in Iran have
set us back, according to economy
minister Katharina Reich. She said at a
press conference in Berlin, "The
situation remains highly volatile." Now,
Germany was not recovering to begin
with, even if the country did manage a
small increase to GDP last year, which
was the first time in 3 years. That
still forgot how to grow, even if the
minus sign itself was reversed, but that
was the only thing that actually
changed. You can have a plus sign, but
if there's nowhere near enough of a plus
sign, you're still in contraction. Now,
officials were hoping it meant much more
than it did, therefore they were raising
their growth projections earlier this
year. But now they have to cut them back
again because even government economists
know that energy shocks come at the
expense of the economy. They aren't
inflationary outside of the initial
short-run impact of prices, but once
that gets to be too much, again, the
race against time, the
the entire economy suffers primarily in
spending and employment. And that brings
us to Scandinavia. Quote, "The jobless
rate jumped last month in Sweden and
Finland as a weaker global outlook
undermines the recovery in two of the
European Union's worst performing labor
markets. And again, there was no
recovery, just a short run slowing in
the rate of contraction. In this case,
rising unemployment that leveled off for
the time being, but since there wasn't a
legit recovery, just a month of higher
energy prices has already triggered an
immediate backlash. Going back to the
article here. Sweden's seasonally
adjusted unemployment rate grew in March
to a 5-month high of 9.2%
above all estimates in a Bloomberg
survey of economists, according to data
from Statistics Sweden on Wednesday,
earlier today. Finland's headline
jobless rate rose to 11.1%,
the highest reading since May 2015, its
statistics office said. So, this is
another example of forgot how to grow
not being understood or appreciated
because of what the DHL guy said.
Without a singular event to focus
everyone's attention, the ongoing flat
beverage world went almost entirely
ignored. Even the central bank in
Sweden, the Riksbank, for example, was
sharply cutting its policy rates as a
response to the weakness, all the while
telling the public it wasn't too bad,
the weakness wasn't too much to get
worked up about, and the rate cuts
themselves wouldn't sure it didn't look
like 2009. Meanwhile, people should have
been asking themselves, if it wasn't
that bad, why did they have to sharply
lower their rates down as low as they
got to be?
But people are left with the impression
that maybe it's somewhat fine when it
hasn't been it's been anything but. And
in case you hadn't noticed from all the
very angry voters, not just in Europe,
they will take out their anger on any
party anywhere who happens to be in
office because nothing changes except
the politics. As I always say, rate of
change in the economy goes down, rate of
change in politics goes way up. And the
energy shock only further depresses the
rate of change in the economy. It's now
even the German government has to change
its projection. So while in Scandinavia,
they were trying to claim things that
were turning around, which wasn't true,
now they can't even say that much. And
the job losses have come back to the UK.
Now the UK payrolls have been back and
forth over the last year, and you can
guess how that has been interpreted.
Every time the payroll number turns
positive, this should sound familiar to
Americans, every time the payroll number
turns positive, everybody shouts about
here comes the recovery, only to be
shocked and surprised in a couple months
when it turns back negative all over
again. The back and forth volatility
between pluses and minuses is still
forgot how to grow a recession, but
nobody noticed it he's absolutely
right. Without that singular event to
focus everyone's attention, you're left
with only two choices. This is what
economists give us. Either the world is
falling apart and off a cliff, or
everything must be fine. That's just
simply not true. And that's before we
even get to the tipping point in the
energy shock.
So British payrolls, they fell
unexpectedly by almost 11,000 in March
after having returned to hourly
contraction back in February. Now as I
said, monthly payrolls have been back
and forth over the last year, which is
very familiar to anyone watching the US
establishment survey do the exact same
thing. That's not good. That's flat
beverage. But every time UK payrolls
pick up, just like in the US, straight
away central bankers, the mainstream,
they declare it the definitive end to
the downturn, only for payrolls to turn
negative all over again just a couple
months later. So we've got British jobs
that are being lost, flat beverage the
same there as here, and hardly anyone
recognizes it because it doesn't look
like 2009. Again, the DHL CEO was right.
Without that big huge event, the massive
layoffs for months, you know, a couple
months in a row, hundreds of thousands
of job losses, the back and forth is
mistaken for resiliency.
But even if it wasn't a contraction, you
toss in there the energy shock and it
really gets to be lights out. Whatever
slim chance there was for a legit
rebound, it just completely disappears
with higher gasoline and diesel, not to
mention what we already went over, the
shortage of physical supply in reality.
Now, as it was, Britain's official
unemployment rate in February, the
latest data that they they put out, that
had dropped to 4.9% from 5.2% in
January, and while that might sound like
a positive, too,
you are if if you've been paying
attention North America, US and Canada,
you're already know it's not. We've
already seen this in both places and the
reason why the jobless rate fell in the
UK rather than increase with the return
of payroll losses
is because British workers have really
started to drop out of the labor force.
Participation,
that one sank and that's even before
getting to Iran and oil. So, former
workers, they stop looking for work
because they know there aren't enough
jobs available. It's one of the worst
signs for a struggling economy because
not only does it confirm the struggle,
lower labor participation also says
workers, they don't believe it's going
to turn around anytime soon, which is
why they stop looking for work, which is
why they drop out. Now, they didn't
actually drop out in reality, they still
want to work, but the government
statistics, the government data drops
them out because it arbitrarily
determines you have to be looking for
work in order to be counted. But what's
the point of looking for work if there's
nothing to look for? And it's a question
too many people all over the world have
been asking themselves the past couple
of years of record high stock prices.
So, the energy shock really is a race
against time. The DHL guy was absolutely
correct about that as well as the fact
that nobody sees the clock or hears it
ticking. Instead, they're focused on the
stock market, official statements,
official projections. It's always going
to be picking up. Christine Lagarde says
it's a good place. Meanwhile, over here
in reality, the weakened economy has
just been hit by another headwind that
it really, really cannot afford.
So, the tipping point that he was
talking about is determined not
necessarily by the price of petroleum or
how long it remains elevated. Those
They're important factors. Even more
important is the state of the economy
before even getting to the shock and
when it first developed. If it truly was
resilient, legitimately strong, then it
could take a big hit. But sadly, the
only resilience has been the rhetoric
coming out of officials whose first and
many times only job is to lie to you
about that very thing. That's exactly
what Christine Lagarde's good place
really is. So, the tipping point, it
might be much closer than you think,
which would mean it wouldn't take nearly
as much of an energy shock to produce
the same outcomes as historical examples
starting with the one from 2022.
Ever since 2022, Europe in particular
has been forgetting more and more how to
grow, remembering more and more how to
flat beverage. Now we're getting signs
and signals and confirmation of the
energy shock on top of everything else.
You've got consumer confidence in a
freefall, commercial and financial
confidence not just in Germany but
across Europe that is legitimately
crashing, unemployment rising in
Scandinavia already hard hit, UK job
losses, participation down there.
If only record high stock prices
actually mattered.
Let's not forget the dollar shock that
goes along with the energy shock. And
the other part of the dollar shock,
which I went over a couple of days ago
that we're seeing now in the UAE and
Dubai, details in the video link below.
As always, thank you very much for
joining me. Huge thank you Euro Dollar
University members and subscribers. And
until next time,
take care.